07 - Future Tasks of the Alliance - “Harmel Report”
NATO Archives Online
- Approval of Final Report during December 1967 Council Ministerial Session in Brussels. (October 1967 – December 1967), 1967-10 - 1967-12; Volume 9; 74 Items
  - On 13th December, 1967, Council in Ministerial Session Approved the Report on the Future Tasks of the Alliance as Amended During Discussion and Subsequently Issued as C-M(67)74 (2nd Revise) – Known as Harmel Report, Section 9
    - FCM(67)221. Typing errors in C-M(67)74: (The Harmel Report) (30 November 1967) ENG 1
    - Italian Delegation. Letter to the Secretary General with the Italian amendments to paragraph 17 of the Harmel Report. (4 December 1967) FRE 1
    - PO(67)878. Private Office. Circulation to all Permanent Representatives of the Italian amendment. (4 December 1967) ENG+FRE 1
    - Portuguese Delegation. Letter to the Secretary General accepting the Italian amendments. (5 December 1967) FRE 1
    - FCM(67)228. Letter from Deputy executive Secretary to Assistant Secretary General, Political Affairs, attaching full bracketed versions from paragraph 10 of the Harmel Report (C-M(67)74). (6 December 1967) ENG+FRE 1
    - Mr. Harmel’s opinion concerning the draft of the Italian amendment to paragraph 17 of the Harmel Report (December 1967). FRE 1
    - Note on what is considered working programme and rationale in the Harmel Report. (7 December 1967) ENG 1
    - C-M(67)74(Revised). Future Tasks of the Alliance, Report of the Council. (13 December 1967) ENG 1
    - Tentative draft of paragraphs for the final communique from the Secretary General to the Delegations. (12 December 1967) ENG 1
    - C-R(67)51. NATO Council ministerial session on 13 December 1967. (14 February 1968). BIL 1
    - Press Communique M4(67)3 Final Communique – for immediate release to the press. (14 December 1967) FRE 1
    - Press Communique M4(67)3 Final Communique – for immediate release to the press. (14 December 1967) ENG 1
    - C-M(67)74 (2nd revise). Future Tasks of the Alliance. Report of the Council. (18 December 1967) FRE 1
    - C-M(67)74 (2nd revise). Future Tasks of the Alliance. Report of the Council. (18 December 1967) ENG 1
    - RS(67)144. Political Affairs Division, Research Section,. Proposed corrections to the final text of Report on Future Tasks of the Alliance from W.M Newton to Deputy Executive Secretary. (18 December 1967) ENG 1
    - Corrigendum to C-M(67)74 (2nd revise) dated 18th December. (20 December 1967) ENG 1
  - Note prepared for lecturers (February, 1968) summarising the development of the study and the content of the Harmel Report, Section 10
    - Notes à l’intention des conférenciers – SN/1. Rapport Harmel: Les futures tâches de l’Alliance. (February 1968) FRE 1
- 50th Anniversary of the Harmel Report - Special Declassification, 1965 - 1969; Volume 10; 23 Items; Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance
  In late 1966, the approaching 20th anniversary of NATO and the adjustments made necessary by the French decision of 1966 to withdraw from the military integrated structure prompted the Alliance to re-examine its relevance and adaptation to the existing political context.
  At the December 1966 NATO Meeting of Foreign Ministers, Pierre Harmel, Belgium’s Foreign Minister, tabled a proposal calling for a joint analysis of the major events of the past twenty years. He recommended the study be used to determine the effect of events on the objectives and methods of the Alliance and decide whether it was necessary to improve consultation within it. The Foreign Affairs Ministers responded favourably to Harmel’s proposal and empowered Manlio Brosio, NATO Secretary General and the Permanent Representatives to the North Atlantic Council (NAC) with a comprehensive mandate to develop procedures for the study and determine its scope.
  In February 1967, the NAC decided to constitute an open-ended Special Group of representatives designated by governments, under the Chairmanship of the Secretary General. The NAC gave the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance (also known under the reference AC/261) the task of studying “ (a) the development of political events as it affects the purposes of the Alliance; (b) the consequent future tasks of the Alliance”. The Special Group was to establish such special procedures, sub-groups and rapporteurs, and request such staff work from the International Staff as it deemed necessary” [ see reference C-M(67)11].
  During the month of March 1967 the Special Group met on five occasions in private session to encourage wide ranging discussions. It was during these meetings that they decided on the framework for the conduct of the study. The Special Group created four sub-groups were created, each working on a broad subject of interest to the Alliance and under the guidance of a rapporteur of repute:
  • Sub-Group One, East/West Relations: Mr. K.Schutz, State Secretary, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Germany and Mr. J.H.A. Watson, Assistant Under Secretary of State. Foreign Affairs, United Kingdom
  • Sub-Group Two, Inter-allied Relations: Mr. Paul-Henri Spaak, Minister of State, Belgium
  • Sub-Group Three, General Defence Policy: Mr. Foy Kohler, Deputy Under Secretary of State, United States
  • Sub-Group Four, Relations with other Countries: Dr. C.L. Patijn, Professor of International Relations, University of Utrecht (Netherlands)
  The NATO International Staff provided secretarial support and was tasked with gathering background material for the sub-groups.
  The sub-groups met several times from May to June to prepare a draft interim report which was approved by the NAC [se reference C-M(67)33] following some amendments at their Ministerial meeting of 13 - 14 June in Luxembourg.
  Following this initial phase, the sub-groups began to address the substantive issues. Although the reports were prepared under the responsibility of each rapporteur, a meeting of all the sub-groups took place in July to harmonise the work and avoid duplication. After having gone through several stages, the reports were reviewed and their findings compared during a last meeting in October at Ditchley Park (UK).
  The following month, the Special Group held a high-level meeting over two days during which the substance of the Report was discussed. The Secretary General circulated a draft Report which was discussed and amended by the Special Group on 22 November 1967.
  The Report on the Future Tasks of the Alliance was presented at the NATO Ministerial Session and after some last amendments was approved by Foreign Affairs Ministers on 14 December 1967 and subsequently released to the press [See reference C-M(67)74(2nd revised) and M4(67)3, respectively].
  This special collection of Private Records of the North Atlantic Council was released to celebrate the 50th Anniversary of the Harmel Report. Private Records were informal notes taken by the Executive Secretary, for the use of the Private Office, of the restricted sessions of the council. The documents shed new light on the development and impact of the Harmel Report.
  - Record of a private meeting of the Council held on Wednesday, 17th March, 1965 at 10.15 a.m., 1965-03-22; PR(65)11; 17 pages
  - Record of a private meeting of the Council held on Wednesday, 17th March, 1965 at 10.15 a.m., 1965-03-22; PR(65)11; 17 pages
    Les informations OTAN mises en lecture publique sont accessibles pour des travaux de recherche et d'enseignement. Toute utilisation de ces informations à des fins commerciales nécessite l'autorisation écrite de l'Organisation. Il faut faire état de l'accord des Archives de l'OTAN pour toute utilisation de documents à des fins de publication. Les instructions quant à la manière de bien donner les références des informations OTAN mises en lecture publique peuvent être trouvées sur le site web des Archives de l'OTAN (http://www.nato.int/archives).
  - Summary record of a private meeting of the Council held on Wednesday, 7th April, 1965 at 10.15 a.m., 1965-04-12; PR(65)16; 5 pages
  - Record of a private meeting of the Council held on Wednesday, 14th April, 1965 at 10.15 a.m., 1965-04-21; PR(65)17-REDACTED COPY; 3 pages
  - Private Meeting of the Council in the Office of the Secretary General, 9th June 1965, 1965-06-09; PR(65)26.2; 4 pages
  - Summary record of a private meeting of the Council held on Friday, 2nd July, 1965 at 3.30 p.m., 1965-07-05; PR(65)32; 4 pages
  - Summary record of a private meeting of the Council held on Wednesday, 24th November, 1965 at 10.15 a.m., 1965-11-24; PR(65)56; 11 pages
  - Summary record of a private meeting of the Council held on Wednesday, 24th November, 1965 at 10.15 a.m., 1965-11-24; PR(65)56; 11 pages
  - Council Meeting with Vice-President Humphrey held on Friday, 7th April 1967, at 3.15 p.m., 1967-04-07; PR(67)13; 9 pages
  - Council Meeting with Vice-President Humphrey held on Friday, 7th April 1967, at 3.15 p.m., 1967-04-07; PR(67)13; 9 pages
  - Procès-verbal d'une réunion privée du Conseil tenue le mercredi 10 octobre 1967, 1967-10-10; PR(67)33; 2 pages
  - Summary Record of a Private Meeting of Permanent Representatives held on Wednesday, 10th October, at 10.30 a.m., 1967-10-19; PR(67)34; 6 pages
  - Summary Record of a Private Meeting of Permanent Representatives held on Wednesday, 25th October, at 3.30 p.m., 1967-10-27; PR(67)36.1; 5 pages
  - Private Record of a meeting of Permanent Representatives held on Wednesday, 17th January, 1968 to discuss the follow-up to the Harmel Report, 1968-01-19; PR(68)1.2; 5 pages
  - Private record of a meeting of Permanent Representatives held on Tuesday, 23rd January, 1968 to continue discussion on the follow-up to the Harmel Report, 1968-01-25; PR(68)2; 2 pages
  - Summary record of a private meeting of the Council on 29th January, 1968, 1968-01-29; PR(68)3-NO ANNEX; 5 pages
  - Record of a private meeting of the Council held on Wednesday, 5th February, 1969, 1969-02-05; PR(69)6; 7 pages
  - Summary Record of a private meeting of the Council held on Saturday, 22nd February, 1969, at 10.30 a.m., 1969-02-27; PR(69)10; 2 pages
  - CONFIDENTIAL SUMMARY NOTES ON A PRIVATE COUNCIL MEETING WITH PRESIDENT NIXON AT 10.25 a.m. ON MONDAY, 24th FEBRUARY, 1969, 1969-02-24; PR(69)11; 15 pages
  - Summary of discussion at the Private Meeting of Ambassadors held in the Secretary General's Office on Tuesday, 29th April, 1969, 1969-04-29; PR(69)24; 9 pages
  - Summary record of a private meeting of the Council held on Wednesday, 9th July, 1969, 1969-07-09; PR(69)36.1; 9 pages
  - Summary record of a private meeting of the Council held on Wednesday, 28th July, 1969, at 16.00 p.m., 1969-08-01; PR(69)42; 25 pages
  - Compte rendu d’une réunion privée du Conseil tenue le lundi 28 juillet à 16 heures, 1969-08-01; PR(69)42; 25 pages